<TEI xmlns="http://www.tei-c.org/ns/1.0">
   <teiHeader>
      <fileDesc>
         <titleStmt>
            <title>A funeral sermon Opening the nature and grounds of assurance, occasioned by the death of Mr. Philip King, Minister. Who departed this life, November, 8th. 1699. By Jonathan Owen.</title>
            <author>Owen, Jonathan.</author>
         </titleStmt>
         <editionStmt>
            <edition>
               <date>1700</date>
            </edition>
         </editionStmt>
         <extent>Approx. 40 KB of XML-encoded text transcribed from 16 1-bit group-IV TIFF page images.</extent>
         <publicationStmt>
            <publisher>Text Creation Partnership,</publisher>
            <pubPlace>Ann Arbor, MI ; Oxford (UK) :</pubPlace>
            <date when="2011-12">2011-12 (EEBO-TCP Phase 2).</date>
            <idno type="DLPS">A53746</idno>
            <idno type="STC">Wing O827</idno>
            <idno type="STC">ESTC R216657</idno>
            <idno type="EEBO-CITATION">99828382</idno>
            <idno type="PROQUEST">99828382</idno>
            <idno type="VID">32809</idno>
            <availability>
               <p>To the extent possible under law, the Text Creation Partnership has waived all copyright and related or neighboring rights to this keyboarded and encoded edition of the work described above, according to the terms of the CC0 1.0 Public Domain Dedication (http://creativecommons.org/publicdomain/zero/1.0/). This waiver does not extend to any page images or other supplementary files associated with this work, which may be protected by copyright or other license restrictions. Please go to https://www.textcreationpartnership.org/ for more information about the project.</p>
            </availability>
         </publicationStmt>
         <seriesStmt>
            <title>Early English books online.</title>
         </seriesStmt>
         <notesStmt>
            <note>(EEBO-TCP ; phase 2, no. A53746)</note>
            <note>Transcribed from: (Early English Books Online ; image set 32809)</note>
            <note>Images scanned from microfilm: (Early English books, 1641-1700 ; 1856:25)</note>
         </notesStmt>
         <sourceDesc>
            <biblFull>
               <titleStmt>
                  <title>A funeral sermon Opening the nature and grounds of assurance, occasioned by the death of Mr. Philip King, Minister. Who departed this life, November, 8th. 1699. By Jonathan Owen.</title>
                  <author>Owen, Jonathan.</author>
               </titleStmt>
               <extent>31, [1] p.   </extent>
               <publicationStmt>
                  <publisher>printed for Tho. Parkhurst at the Bible and Three Crowns in Cheapside near Mercers-Chapel,</publisher>
                  <pubPlace>London :</pubPlace>
                  <date>1700.</date>
               </publicationStmt>
               <notesStmt>
                  <note>Reproduction of the original in the Edinburgh University Library.</note>
               </notesStmt>
            </biblFull>
         </sourceDesc>
      </fileDesc>
      <encodingDesc>
         <projectDesc>
            <p>Created by converting TCP files to TEI P5 using tcp2tei.xsl,
      TEI @ Oxford.
      </p>
         </projectDesc>
         <editorialDecl>
            <p>EEBO-TCP is a partnership between the Universities of Michigan and Oxford and the publisher ProQuest to create accurately transcribed and encoded texts based on the image sets published by ProQuest via their Early English Books Online (EEBO) database (http://eebo.chadwyck.com). The general aim of EEBO-TCP is to encode one copy (usually the first edition) of every monographic English-language title published between 1473 and 1700 available in EEBO.</p>
            <p>EEBO-TCP aimed to produce large quantities of textual data within the usual project restraints of time and funding, and therefore chose to create diplomatic transcriptions (as opposed to critical editions) with light-touch, mainly structural encoding based on the Text Encoding Initiative (http://www.tei-c.org).</p>
            <p>The EEBO-TCP project was divided into two phases. The 25,368 texts created during Phase 1 of the project (2000-2009), initially available only to institutions that contributed to their creation, were released into the public domain on 1 January 2015. The approximately 40,000 texts produced during Phase 2 (2009- ), of which 34,963 had been released as of 2020, originally similarly restricted, were similarly freed from all restrictions on 1 August 2020. As of that date anyone is free to take and use these texts for any purpose (modify them, annotate them, distribute them, etc.). But we do respectfully request that due credit and attribution be given to their original source.</p>
            <p>Users should be aware of the process of creating the TCP texts, and therefore of any assumptions that can be made about the data.</p>
            <p>Text selection was based on the New Cambridge Bibliography of English Literature (NCBEL). If an author (or for an anonymous work, the title) appears in NCBEL, then their works are eligible for inclusion. Selection was intended to range over a wide variety of subject areas, to reflect the true nature of the print record of the period. In general, first editions of a works in English were prioritized, although there are a number of works in other languages, notably Latin and Welsh, included and sometimes a second or later edition of a work was chosen if there was a compelling reason to do so.</p>
            <p>Image sets were sent to external keying companies for transcription and basic encoding. Quality assurance was then carried out by editorial teams in Oxford and Michigan. 5% (or 5 pages, whichever is the greater) of each text was proofread for accuracy and those which did not meet QA standards were returned to the keyers to be redone. After proofreading, the encoding was enhanced and/or corrected and characters marked as illegible were corrected where possible up to a limit of 100 instances per text. Any remaining illegibles were encoded as &lt;gap&gt;s. Understanding these processes should make clear that, while the overall quality of TCP data is very good, some errors will remain and some readable characters will be marked as illegible. Users should bear in mind that in all likelihood such instances will never have been looked at by a TCP editor.</p>
            <p>The texts were encoded and linked to page images in accordance with level 4 of the TEI in Libraries guidelines.</p>
            <p>Copies of the texts have been issued variously as SGML (TCP schema; ASCII text with mnemonic sdata character entities); displayable XML (TCP schema; characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or text strings within braces); or lossless XML (TEI P5, characters represented either as UTF-8 Unicode or TEI g elements).</p>
            <p>Keying and markup guidelines are available at the <ref target="http://www.textcreationpartnership.org/docs/.">Text Creation Partnership web site</ref>.</p>
         </editorialDecl>
         <listPrefixDef>
            <prefixDef ident="tcp"
                       matchPattern="([0-9\-]+):([0-9IVX]+)"
                       replacementPattern="http://eebo.chadwyck.com/downloadtiff?vid=$1&amp;page=$2"/>
            <prefixDef ident="char"
                       matchPattern="(.+)"
                       replacementPattern="https://raw.githubusercontent.com/textcreationpartnership/Texts/master/tcpchars.xml#$1"/>
         </listPrefixDef>
      </encodingDesc>
      <profileDesc>
         <langUsage>
            <language ident="eng">eng</language>
         </langUsage>
         <textClass>
            <keywords scheme="http://authorities.loc.gov/">
               <term>King, Philip, d. 1699 --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Bible. --  O.T. --  Job XIX, 25. --  Sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Funeral sermons --  Early works to 1800.</term>
               <term>Sermons, English --  17th century.</term>
            </keywords>
         </textClass>
      </profileDesc>
      <revisionDesc>
         <change>
            <date>2010-08</date>
            <label>TCP</label>Assigned for keying and markup</change>
         <change>
            <date>2010-09</date>
            <label>SPi Global</label>Keyed and coded from ProQuest page images</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Sampled and proofread</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-02</date>
            <label>Olivia Bottum</label>Text and markup reviewed and edited</change>
         <change>
            <date>2011-06</date>
            <label>pfs</label>Batch review (QC) and XML conversion</change>
      </revisionDesc>
   </teiHeader>
   <text xml:lang="eng">
      <front>
         <div type="title_page">
            <pb facs="tcp:32809:1"/>
            <p>A FUNERAL SERMON. Opening the Nature and Grounds OF ASSURANCE, Occaſioned by the DEATH OF M<hi rend="sup">r</hi>. <hi>Philip King,</hi> Miniſter. Who Departed this Life, <hi>No<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vember,</hi> 8th. 1699.</p>
            <p>By <hi>JONATHAN OWEN.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>
               <hi>LONDON:</hi> Printed for: <hi>Tho. Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three-Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mercers</hi>-Chapel. 1700.</p>
         </div>
         <div type="letter">
            <pb facs="tcp:32809:2"/>
            <pb facs="tcp:32809:2"/>
            <head>To the Church of Chriſt, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gregating in <hi>Dead-Mans-Place Southwark,</hi> the Author wiſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>eth, that all Grace and Peace may abound.</head>
            <opener>
               <salute>Beloved in our Lord,</salute>
            </opener>
            <p>GOD by his merciful Provi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dence hath yet continued us together in the ſacred Bonds of the glorious Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel; and it is my earneſt Prayer and Deſire, that we may ſtedfaſt<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly keep the <g ref="char:V">Ʋ</g>nity of the Spirit in the Bond of Peace and Love. Amongſt the many Afflictions which have attended my Courſe in the Miniſtry, this hath been none of the leaſt; to wit, the too little Service which I have done for Chriſt and immortal Souls; yet I thank<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fully acknowledge to the God of all Grace, it is none of my Fear, that I have laboured altogether in vain; ſome of you I have eſpouſed to Chriſt, others
<pb facs="tcp:32809:3"/>by my Poor endeavours have been built up in him; what the Bleſſed Apoſtle writes to the <hi>Corinthians</hi> is verified in ſome meaſure amongſt you, <hi>1</hi> Epiſt. <hi>1.</hi> Chap. <hi>27, 28.</hi> yea God is my Witneſs, I wou'd gladly ſpend and be ſpent for you, it's Ability and not Will which is wanting to Anſwer your affectionate Expectations in all things; when your Sympathy ſomewhat eaſed me, the Lord directed, you to one richly anointed for his Maſters Work: But ah alas! Mr. <hi>P. K.</hi> is removed in the Morning of his Days, in the Twen<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ty Fourth Year of his Age; when your Eyes and Heart were much upon him, it may be too much, for to know Miniſters after the Fleſh is the ſpeedy way to be rid of them; thoſe Feet which were beautiful in bringing glad-tidings, ſhall walk with you and ſpeak to you no more: O that all ſuch humbling Providences might be wiſely improved! The Voice of the Rod ſpeaks loud and plain, comply with it for the Lord's ſake; for what Reaſons I was loth to undertake this Province you know; but I can deny no reaſonable Requeſt to your concurrant Deſires; and now what you all would
<pb facs="tcp:32809:3"/>have, hath not only come to your Ear, but alſo to your Eye, and into your Hands; it may be this will abide with many of you, when ſhortly it will be ſaid of me, as now of the more Worthy, that I am gone alſo: What may be the cenſures of ſome I know not, and if you be profited I ſhall leſs Matter. This with hearty Prayers for each other; is what I propound, and deſire, whilſt I am Living; and your</p>
            <closer>
               <signed>
                  <hi>Unworthy Paſtor,</hi> Jonathan Owen.</signed>
            </closer>
         </div>
         <div type="publishers_advertisement">
            <pb facs="tcp:32809:4"/>
            <head>Books, lately Printed for <hi>Thomas Parkhurſt</hi> at the <hi>Bible</hi> and <hi>Three Crowns</hi> in <hi>Cheapſide</hi> near <hi>Mer<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cers-Chapel.</hi>
            </head>
            <list>
               <item>MR. <hi>Adams</hi>'s Funeral Sermon.</item>
               <item>A Diſcourſe concerning the Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ers Dominion over the Inviſible Worlds; ſome Part whereof was Preach'd on the Occa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſion of the Death of <hi>John Houghton</hi> Eſquire.</item>
               <item>Dr. <hi>Bates</hi>'s Funeral Sermon.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Mead</hi>'s Funeral Sermon.</item>
               <item>All Four by the Reverend Mr. <hi>John Howe.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Of the Shortneſs of Time. By <hi>F. Fuller.</hi>
               </item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Bradford</hi>'s Eight Sermons Preach'd at St. <hi>Pauls,</hi> at the Lecture founded by the Ho<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nourable <hi>Robert Boyle</hi> Eſquire.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Philip Henry</hi>'s Life.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Reynold</hi>'s Miniſter of <hi>Notingham</hi> his Life.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Math. Henry</hi>'s Diſcourſe of Meekneſs.</item>
               <item>Mr. <hi>Joſeph Barrett</hi>'s Funeral Sermon, to which is annexed his Life, <hi>&amp;c.</hi>
               </item>
            </list>
         </div>
      </front>
      <body>
         <div type="sermon">
            <pb facs="tcp:32809:4"/>
            <head>A FUNERAL SERMON: Opening the Nature and Grounds OF ASSURANCE, Occaſioned by the DEATH OF Mr. <hi>Philip King,</hi> Miniſter.</head>
            <epigraph>
               <q>
                  <bibl>
                     <hi>JOB XIX. XXV.</hi>
                  </bibl>
                  <p>For I know that my Redeemer liveth.</p>
               </q>
            </epigraph>
            <p>HOLY <hi>Job</hi> was an eminent In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtance of Grace, he had this ſin<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gular Honour put upon him, <hi>viz,</hi> Heavens Teſtimony that he was a non-ſuch for true Piety, <hi>ver.</hi> 8. Never was Saint upon Earth exerciſed with Affli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctions like him; they came upon him as the Waves of the Sea. The <hi>Sabbeans</hi> and the <hi>Caldeans,</hi> Wind and Storms ſwept all away; his Wife ſeemeth to be ſpared only to add
<pb n="8" facs="tcp:32809:5"/>to his Sorrows; all his Friends were miſera<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble Comforters, ſuch that added unto, and aggravated his Calamities, <hi>Chap.</hi> 16.2. His admirable Patience doth thus appear, to wit, in all he exalted God, and debaſed him<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſelf, <hi>Chap.</hi> 1.21. <hi>The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, and bleſſed be the Name of the Lord.</hi> Chap. 7.20. <hi>I have ſinned;</hi> there is his great Self-abaſement. In this Chapter, he proceeds to maintain his Inte<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grity againſt <hi>Bildad;</hi> he chargeth <hi>Job</hi> very high, he loads him with black Crimes, and numbers him with the vileſt of Men, ſuch that knew not God, as you may ſee in <hi>Chap.</hi> 18. But to fall upon the Text, it contains the Reaſon of his Defence and foregoing Option, and the Grounds of his inward Support under all his outward Afflictions. Therein more Particularly you have Two Things.</p>
            <p n="1">1. A full and Clear Confeſſion of <hi>Job</hi>'s Faith. Reſpecting the Perſon, Office, and Glory of Jeſus Chriſt; his Perſon, that he is really and truly God. So he expreſly calls him, <hi>In my Fleſh ſhall I ſee God,</hi> ver. 26. His Office, a Redeemer of loſt and inthrald Sinners; his Glory, both Preſent and Fu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture; his Preſent Glory, a living Redeem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; his Future, in the latter part of the Verſe, <hi>He ſhall ſtand at the latter Day upon the Earth:</hi> i. e. He ſhall come in our Na<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ture to Judge the World, and Triumph over all his Enemies.</p>
            <p n="2">
               <pb n="9" facs="tcp:32809:5"/>
2. You have here, the Nature, Kind, and Degree of Holy <hi>Job</hi>'s Faith, it was not a common but a ſpecial Faith, not a dead but a living Faith, not a weak but ſtrong Faith, not a doubting but a Plerophory, a full Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of Faith, <hi>I know that my Redeemer li<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veth;</hi> having thus briefly open'd the Words, behold an Ocean of ſpiritual Matter preſents it ſelf, we may venture to Launch into it; and how pleaſant will it be, if we are wrapt up in the raviſhing Contemplations thereof, as the Deceaſed often was in ſuch Work; and that remarkably, in his laſt Diſcourſes upon glorying in nothing but the Croſs of Chriſt. The</p>
            <p>Doct. <hi>They are great and rare Inſtances of Grace, who like</hi> Job, <hi>can ſay,</hi> They know that their Redeemer liveth, <hi>i. e. That can ſay it upon Scripture Grounds. Would to God we were all come up to this Grace, ſince it is poſſible with a Holy Ambition, let us aſpire after it.</hi>
            </p>
            <p>The Method of proſecuting this Point ſhall be thus, if the Lord will.</p>
            <p n="1">I. To Premiſe two Things for Illuſtrati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on.</p>
            <p n="2">II. To ſet before you the Scripture Foun<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dation of a well-grounded Aſſurance.</p>
            <p n="3">III. I ſhall confirm this Truth, by demon<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtrating the greatneſs and rarity of this Grace.</p>
            <p n="4">
               <pb n="10" facs="tcp:32809:6"/>
IV. The Practical Improvement of the whole, with reſpect to the ſad Occaſion thereof.</p>
            <p>The two Things to be premiſed are theſe.</p>
            <p n="1">1. There are but few that can ſay from Scripture-Foundation, <hi>They know that their Redeemer liveth;</hi> this is not more ſad then true, it is facile, eaſie and common to re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>peat the Words, but it is peculiar and rare to find thoſe who upon the like footing as <hi>Job</hi> can thus expreſs themſelves; <hi>Zeph.</hi> 1.12. There God ſpeaks of ſearching <hi>Jeruſalem</hi> as with Candles, which denotes the exactneſs of the Scrutiny, ſo if we make the moſt di<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ligent inquiry into the Lives and Experien<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces of moſt Men and Women. O where are the Perſons that can or may thus warranta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly declare themſelves; <hi>I know that my Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer liveth,</hi> among them that profeſs Chriſt in a more exact way then others, that hear more of his Perſon, Office, and Glory, as Redeemer; even among theſe it is a rare thing, moſt are but come up to Hopes, and but few to the <hi>good Hope through Grace,</hi> that which maketh not aſhamed, 2 <hi>Theſſ.</hi> 2.16.</p>
            <p n="2">2. For as I would awaken all, ſo I would not caſt down any of Chriſts weak Lambs. We that Preach the Word, muſt with <hi>Boa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nerges</hi> Thunder, and with <hi>Barnabas</hi> ſpeak Conſolation to you; therefore know, it is poſſible to be intereſted in Chriſt, and not
<pb n="11" facs="tcp:32809:6"/>be fully aſſured of it; Aſſurance is not of the Eſſence of Chriſtianity, it is but acci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dental, like <hi>Benjamins</hi> Meſs, it is a peculiar Favour; they were as really <hi>Joſephs</hi> Brethren that had it not as he; you may be of Chriſts Brotherhood by adopting Grace, and yet be without it: If Aſſurance were of the Eſſence of Grace, then none could be ſaved but ſuch; this makes the number of the Bleſſed Saints Ten Thouſand Times fewer then they are, it excludes all Dead Infants out of Heaven; indeed what the Apoſtle ſaith is remarka<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble, 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.10. <hi>He that believeth on the Son of God, hath the Witneſs in himſelf:</hi> But conſider, as it is ſpoken of Adult Perſons, ſo it refers to the Three-fold Witneſs ſpo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ken off before; <hi>viz.</hi> the Spirit, the Water, and the Blood, now every Adult Believer hath this Witneſs in himſelf; but alas, it of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tentimes ſo falls out, that the Ear of Faith is ſo Deaf, and the Eye of Faith ſo dim, and Hand of Faith ſo weak, that the renewed Believer neither hears, ſees, nor receives his own Mercy's as he ought; many a doubting Saint hath got ſafe to Glory, when carnal Confidents have dropt into Hell-Flames; a Child may be born Heir to a great Eſtate, and by reaſon of his Infancy not know it; it as Birth and Blood which gives right to it, not the preſent Senſe and Knowledge of the thing; this renders the Matter comfortable, the other makes the Thing ſure; thus much of what I thought needful to be Premiſed,
<pb n="12" facs="tcp:32809:7"/>but few know upon Scripture Bottom, <hi>that their Redeemer liveth,</hi> it is poſſible to be ſa<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>vingly intereſted in Chriſt, and yet not know it certainly. I enter upon the ſecond General.</p>
            <p n="2">2. What is that Scripture-Foundation, which this full Aſſurance of Faith <hi>(I know, that my Redeemer liveth)</hi> muſt be Built up<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on. Here take Notice, for it is without Controverſie; this Aſſurance hath its Origi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nal in Grace, and not in Nature; true, a natural Man may be endued with great Knowledge, his Head may be full of Specu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lative Underſtanding about Divine Things, he may come under very powerful and com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mon workings of the Spirit, and yet be without a Foundation for this; ſo much the Apoſtle declares, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.4, 5. Now that I may ſet this weighty Matter before you in the plain Light of the Word, to know that ones Redeemer liveth, it is and muſt be built upon this Threefold Foundation, <hi>viz.</hi>
            </p>
            <list>
               <item>1. The ſaving Knowledge of Chriſt.</item>
               <item>2. The appropriating Acts of Faith.</item>
               <item>3. And the Witneſs of the Spirit.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. Chriſt Jeſus in his Perſon, Office and Glory as Redeemer muſt be revealed to that Soul: Without this Manifeſtation of Chriſt no Man can ſay it; though ignorant and con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fident Perſons may Orally ſpeak the Words, but he that doth it with this Faith, muſt know
<pb n="13" facs="tcp:32809:7"/>in whom he believeth, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. The Glory of God, in the Face, or Perſon of Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus Chriſt, muſt ſhine into that Heart, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 6.4. <hi>For God who commanded the Light to ſhine out of Darkneſs, hath ſhin'd into our Hearts, to give the Light of the Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge of the Glory of God, in the Face of Jeſus Chriſt.</hi> All this is evident from <hi>Jobs</hi> Confeſſion, let me conſider it a little far<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ther.</p>
            <p n="1">1. He knew the Lord Jeſus Chriſt in his Perſon; <hi>i. e.</hi> He knew him to be really God, eternally, naturally, and eſſentially God, therefore he expreſly ſo calls him; <hi>ver.</hi> 26. <hi>Though after my Skin, Worms deſtroy this Body, yet in my Fleſh ſhall I ſee God: Whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf.</hi> The glorious Diſplay which Chriſt will make of himſelf in the latter Day, all ſhall ſee, ſome to their E<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ternal Horror and Confuſion, and ſome to their Everlaſting Joy; all the redeemed ſhall ſee and enjoy Chriſt, then not one ſhall be diſappointed or miſſing; but thoſe who are ſeal'd with the Holy Spirit of Promiſe, they know it aſſuredly; <hi>Whom I ſhall ſee for my ſelf,</hi> ver. 27.</p>
            <p n="2">2. A well-grounded Aſſurance, includes, not only the Knowledge of Chriſts Perſon as God, but alſo an Acquaintance with his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>fices as Redeemer in both Natures, the Lord Jeſus by Eternal and Foederal Agreement with his Father, is become a Redeemer; Holy <hi>Job</hi> had the Knowledge and Fore-ſight
<pb n="14" facs="tcp:32809:8"/>of this, he not only acknowledgeth Chriſt to be a Redeemer, but he confeſſeth him to be his living Redeemer. Chriſt redeemeth his two ways, by Price and Power, by the Price of Satisfaction paid to the Honour, Law, and Juſtice of God; to his Honour, by the Death of one, <hi>who thought it no rob<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bery to be equal with him,</hi> Phil. 2.6. To his Law, by the perfect Obedience of Chriſts own ſelf, <hi>who was under it,</hi> Gal 4.4. To his Juſtice, by being made a Curſe, <hi>i. e.</hi> his indu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ring the Subſtance thereof, <hi>Gal.</hi> 3.13. As thus by Price, ſo by Power the Lord Jeſus Chriſt redeems Souls, he hath already con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>quer'd, Sin, Death, Hell, and the Grave by his Almighty Power: He is now conquering Sinners to himſelf by the Miniſtry of the Word and Spirit, and yet a little while, and the laſt Trump ſhall ſound, and the Dead in the Bowels of the Earth, and in Depths of the Sea, ſhall hear his Voice and come to Judgment, <hi>John</hi> 5.28, 29. <hi>They that have done good, to the Reſurrection of Life, and they that have done evil unto the Reſurrection of Damnation;</hi> then Chriſt will compleat the Redemption of his People, their Bodies and Souls ſhall be reunited, they ſhall all appear with him in Glory.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As the Knowledge of Chriſts Perſon and Office, is included in this Aſſurance; ſo likewiſe, the Knowledge of his Preſent and Future Glory; to wit, that he now liveth, and ſhall ſtand upon the Earth at the latter
<pb n="15" facs="tcp:32809:8"/>Day; <hi>he liveth,</hi> there is much in that Ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſſion; it Points at the Eternity, Fulneſs and Power of Chriſt as Redeemer; his Eter<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nity, that as God he hath Life in and from himſelf; his Fulneſs, that he hath Life to give to all his Members; and his Power, that, as he lives by his own ſelf, ſo he will quicken the Dead, and Judge the World in Righteouſneſs; and ſhew, that he hath <hi>the Keys of Hell and Death,</hi> Rev. 1.18. But,</p>
            <p n="2">2. In a well-grounded Aſſurance of an Intereſt in the living Redeemer; the Faith of a renewed Soul muſt appropriate Chriſt to himſelf; ſee how <hi>Jobs</hi> Faith wrought, he not only owns Chriſt to be a Redeemer; but his Faith cleaves faſt to him, it graples hard upon him, and it receives him with the whole Heart; <hi>my Redeemer,</hi> therein lies the appropriating Act of his Faith; <hi>Luther</hi> was wont to ſay, that the ſweet of the Go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſpel lay much in Pronouns. <hi>My Lord, and my God,</hi> ſaith <hi>Thomas,</hi> John 20.28. <hi>Who lo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved me, and gave himſelf for me,</hi> ſaith <hi>Paul,</hi> Gal. 2.20. When <hi>Job</hi> loſt all his earthly En<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>joyments, he did not looſe his Intereſt in Chriſt; when he could not ſay my Wealth and worldly Subſtance, my Living, Sons and Daughters; then in the Aſſurance of Faith, he could ſay, my living Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer; when nothing upon Earth could yield him Comfort, then his Faith fetcht it from his living Redeemer; when he was ſtript of all, this remain'd, and indeed it is
<pb n="16" facs="tcp:32809:9"/>
               <hi>that good Part, which ſhall not be taken away,</hi> Luke 10.42.</p>
            <p n="3">3. To conſtitute a well-grounded Aſſu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rance of an Intereſt in the Living Redeemer, there muſt be the Witneſs of the Spirit; the Spirit muſt not only Witneſs to the Perſon and Office of Chriſt as Redeemer, but alſo unto a Mans Perſonal Intereſt in him; not only did all the Prophets give Witneſs unto Chriſt, <hi>Acts</hi> 10.44. But his Incarnati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on and Baptiſm, his Death, Reſurrection and Aſcenſion, does put this Matter out of Doubt; (but herein <hi>Jobs</hi> Faith excels ours,) he believed on the Redeemer to come in the Fleſh, but we upon Him now cloathed with our Nature; he foreſaw the Eternal Word to be made Fleſh, but we muſt believe upon Chriſt <hi>God manifeſt in the Fleſh,</hi> 1 Tom. 3. laſt. <hi>and received up into Glory.</hi> As this is the obje<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctive Faith of Aſſurance, ſo to inable the Soul to ſay, <hi>my Redeemer liveth,</hi> there muſt be the internal ſubjective Witneſs of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit, <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.16. <hi>The Spirit it ſelf beareth Wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſs with our Spirits, that we are the Children of God:</hi> Here you have two Things, the Witneſs, and the Matter witneſſed. The Witneſs is the Spirit, and the Matter wit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>neſſed unto, is Adoption, and ſurely, Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience inlightened and ſanctified, muſt <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap> the Court where this Witneſs is heard and received; ſo then, what can this Witneſs <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 word">
                  <desc>〈◊〉</desc>
               </gap>, but the Holy Spirits ſo inlightning the Mind, and perſwading the Will, that Con<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſcience
<pb n="17" facs="tcp:32809:9"/>muſt conclude that Chriſt is recei<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ved, with the Priviledge to be a Son of God, <hi>John</hi> 1.12. <hi>But as many as receiv'd him to them gave he Power to become the Sons of God, even to them that believe on his Name.</hi> Holy <hi>Job</hi> had this Witneſs within himſelf, and this bore him up againſt all the reproach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>es of his miſerable Comforters; thus you ſee upon what Foundation this Aſſertion is built. Can we ſay, <hi>That we know our Redeemer liveth?</hi> then Chriſt in his Perſon, Chriſt in his Of<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ces, and Chriſt in his Glory, as Redeemer, muſt be known to us, then Faith muſt thus appropriate him, then the Spirit muſt thus Witneſs our perſonal Intereſt in him.</p>
            <p>I proceed to the Third General.</p>
            <p n="3">3. Which is to Confirm the Doctrine, to wit, that they are great and rare Inſtances of Grace, who can ſay with Holy <hi>Job, They know that their Redeemer liveth, i. e.</hi> that can ſay it upon Scripture Foundation; now that ſuch Inſtances are both great and rare, thus appears.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. From their Paucity.</item>
               <item>2. From their Excellency of Spirit.</item>
               <item>3. From their Chriſtian Deportment, with reſpect to Death and Judgment; of theſe a little, which alſo is their excelling.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. If we conſider the Paucity of theſe In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances they muſt be rare; the ſcarcity of a thing oftentimes makes it rare; if Gold were as plenty as Silver, it would be leſs valua<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ble
<pb n="18" facs="tcp:32809:10"/>then it is; this celeſtial Jewel (a well<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>grounded Aſſurance) it is lodged in the Breaſt but of very few, more are Poor with much Wealth, then are Rich in the full Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance of Faith. Since Chriſts Flock is but little comparatively, as he aſſures us, <hi>Luke</hi> 12.32. Therefore the number of ſealed Souls cannot be great; as Holy <hi>Job</hi> was a non-ſuch in his Day, ſo there are but a few ſuch in ours. Not many do attain to Aſſurance, and them that are indulged with it, do not always hold it; it is got in great Diligence, and it is kept with no leſs. This the Apoſtle plain<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly hints, <hi>Heb.</hi> 6.11, 12. <hi>And we deſire, that every one of you do ſhew the ſame Diligence, to the full Aſſurance of Hope unto the End; that ye be not ſlothful, but followers of them, who through Faith and Patience inherit the Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſes.</hi> Who doth not hence perceive, that our utmoſt Diligence, and a well-grounded Aſſurance, are inſeparably Connext? Such Inſtances muſt be rare, becauſe they are but few.</p>
            <p n="2">2. The rarity and greatneſs of ſuch In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſtances of Grace, appears from their Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency of Spirit; and that, with Reſpect to their knowing, doing, and ſuffering the Will of God; Scripture-certified Saints, are Perſons of a choice Spirit, when Holy <hi>Jobs</hi> Body was rough caſt with Ulcers, Boils, and Sores, then his precious Soul like the Kings Daughter was all glorious within, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 45.13. He upon the Dunghil, was in
<pb n="19" facs="tcp:32809:10"/>Gods eſteem a rare Jewel. So the ſacred Scriptures ſtile the Saints, <hi>Mal.</hi> 3.17. <hi>They ſhall be mine, ſaith the Lord of Hoſt, in that Day when I make up my Jewels.</hi> What the Holy Ghoſt remarks concerning <hi>Caleb,</hi> for his eminent Zeal, his undaunted Courage, and conſtant Obedience is applicable unto theſe Darlings of Heaven, well aſſured Souls, <hi>Numb.</hi> 14.24. <hi>But my Servant Caleb becauſe he had another Spirit with him, and hath followed me fully, him will I bring into the Land whereinto he went, and his Seed ſhall poſſeſs it.</hi> Mark, God ſeldom makes great Promiſes to the faithful, but his Heart is al<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſo towards their Children, <hi>his Seed ſhall poſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſeſs it;</hi> ſo in like manner, thoſe that are ſealed with the Holy Spirit of Promiſe; and therefore can ſay, <hi>their Redeemer liveth,</hi> they are Men and Women of choice and eminent Spirits; and this excellency of Spirit chiefly conſiſts in theſe three Things, to wit.</p>
            <list>
               <item>1. In their clear knowing.</item>
               <item>2. In their faithful doing.</item>
               <item>3. In their patient Suffering the Will of God; let me inſiſt upon theſe a little.</item>
            </list>
            <p n="1">1. They have another Spirit of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, than what other Perſons commonly have; That a Mind ſavingly inlightned in the great Truths of the Goſpel is neceſſary unto a well grounded Aſſurance, I need not ſtand to prove, <hi>Job</hi> witneſſeth it in the Text, <hi>I know that my Redeemer liveth,</hi> and you have read what <hi>Paul</hi> ſaith of himſelf to
<pb n="20" facs="tcp:32809:11"/>this Purpoſe, 2. <hi>Tim.</hi> 1.12. <hi>I know whom I have believed, and I am perſwaded, that be is able to keep that which I have committed unto him againſt that Day.</hi> I ſhall not now inſiſt upon the ſpecifick Difference, which is be<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tween common and ſpecial Knowledge. You may be ſure, it is more then gradeal. <hi>Jobs</hi> Friends were Men of exquiſite Parts, they were indued with a great meaſure of excel<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>lent Underſtanding; but in all which they have elegantly ſaid, concerning the Nature, Perfections, Attributes, and Providence of God, how little is there made of Chriſt the Redeemer? But ſee how full, clear, and ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>preſs Holy <hi>Job</hi> is in this Matter. Was Chriſt in our Nature a living Redeemer, in the Decree, Purpoſe, and Promiſe of God the Father? This <hi>Job</hi> knew. Was he actually to come in the Fleſh, and therein to Die and Satisfie for the Sins of his People? <hi>Job</hi> was not ignorant of this. Will he at the latter Day ſtand upon the Earth, and appear in a moſt glorious Manner; and then ſhall all that believe unto Salvation admire him, and ſee him for themſelves? Why Holy <hi>Job</hi> was inſtructed into all this, herein alſo lay his excellent Knowledge; as Heaven gave a ſingular Teſtimony to his Godlineſs, ſo that of the Pſalmiſt was verified in him, <hi>Pſalm</hi> 25.14. <hi>The ſecret of the Lord is with them that fear him; and he will ſhew them his Covenant.</hi> The Glory of God in the Face of Jeſus ſhone into his Heart, he knew
<pb n="21" facs="tcp:32809:11"/>him to be a Redeemer, and his living Re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deemer.</p>
            <p n="2">2. As they have another Spirit of Know<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ledge, ſo alſo of Obedience unto the reveal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Will of God; (but miſtake me not here,) I do not alledge that our Obedience is the Spring and Foundation of Goſpel Aſſurance; no, no, the Faith of Aſſurance looks high<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>er; and through all this, to expect it from thence in our imperfect State, is but loſt la<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bour; ſuch will always be doubtful and flu<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ctuating about it; if <hi>Adams</hi> perfect Obedi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ence did not ſecure the Love of God to him, muchleſs can our imperfect; this Aſſurance comes in at the Door of Faith, from Faiths eyeing of, from Faiths relying upon, and improving the Perſon, Offices, and Glo<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry of the Redeemer. Obedience can't give it, but it always evidenceth that it is well grounded. Remember I am ſhewing the Rarity of this Grace, from that excellent Spirit of Obedience, which goes along with it. And this Obedience flows from the right Principles of Faith in Chriſt, and Love to God; it's managed by the Rule of the Word, and proſecuted unto the Glory of God. Thus they adorn the Doctrine of God their Saviour in all things, thus they obſerve whatſoever he hath commanded them, and thus they deſire to ſtand compleat in the whole Will of God; like as the Nee<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dle in the Compaſs, inclines to the right Point, ſo ſuch is the Divine Vertue of a well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed
<pb n="22" facs="tcp:32809:12"/>Aſſurance, it prompts the Subjects of it to reſpect every Divine Command. The Lan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>guage of their Holy Souls, is like to that of <hi>Samuel,</hi> 1 Sam. 3.9. <hi>Speak Lord for thy Servant heareth.</hi> Or like that of <hi>Saul,</hi> when our Lord ſpake vocally unto him from Hea<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ven, and miraculouſly Converted him to the Faith of himſelf, <hi>Acts</hi> 9.6. <hi>Lord, what wilt thou have me to do?</hi> No ſooner was the Will and Work of his perſecuted Lord revealed unto him, but his whole Self, Soul and Body was ingaged in it, his Head and Heart ſhall contrive, his Mouth ſhall boldly ſpeak, and his Feet take many a weary ſtep to pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>pagate the glorious Goſpel of the Bleſſed Je<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſus. This is that eminency of Obedience which aſſured Souls are inſpired with.</p>
            <p n="3">3. As they have another Spirit of Emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nency for knowing and doing, ſo they have alſo for Suffering the Will of God; the So<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>veraign Lord of all Things, hath wiſely or<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>der'd that his Servants ſhould meet with Tribulations in this World, I ſay with ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny, much, and great, Tribulations, <hi>John</hi> 16. <hi>laſt. In the World ye ſhall have Tribulation.</hi> Acts 14.22. <hi>Through much Tribulation we muſt enter into the Kingdom of God.</hi> Thoſe that had <hi>waſhed their Robes, and made them White in the Blood of the Lamb, are ſaid to come out of great Tribulation,</hi> Rev. 7.14. Now it is not the Moral Vertue, but the Chriſtian Grace of Patience which glorifies God in Afflictions; it is Patience excited by a living
<pb n="23" facs="tcp:32809:12"/>Faith, Patience exerted by a Divine Love; ſuch is that eminency of Spirit which is in a well-grounded Aſſurance, they according to our Lords Injunction, <hi>In your Patience poſſeſs ye your Souls,</hi> Luke 21.19. <hi>i. e.</hi> They enjoy themſelves in Chriſt, when they poſſeſs lit<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tle or nothing elſe, <hi>Job</hi> was not only emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent for his Faith of Aſſurance, but alſo for his ſingular and exemplary Patience; others have been inabled to ſay, <hi>they know that their Redeemer liveth:</hi> But none (except Chriſt) did ever match him in Patience, though <hi>Job</hi> was not perfect and without fault, yet he was a Non-ſuch for Patience; in all his Afflicti<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ons, he highly exalts the Soveraignty, Wiſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>dom, Holineſs and Juſtice of God; ſaying, <hi>The Lord gave, and the Lord hath taken away, bleſſed be the Name of the Lord,</hi> Job 1.21. in all his Tribulations, he greatly debaſed himſelf, ſaying, <hi>I have ſinned,</hi> Job 7.20. And therefore the Holy Ghoſt puts a ſpeci<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>al mark of Honour upon him, <hi>James</hi> 5.10. <hi>We have heard of the Patience of Job:</hi> Well-aſſured Saints are eminent Inſtances of Grace in regard of their patient Suffering the Will of God; let me add one Argument more to confirm this Point.</p>
            <p n="3">3. The greatneſs and rarity of this Grace (a well grounded Aſſurance of an Intereſt in Chriſt) further appears in their Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umphing over Death, Hell, and the Grave, with their patient waiting for Chriſts par<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ticular and general coming to Judge the
<pb n="24" facs="tcp:32809:13"/>World. Chriſt hath conquer'd Death, Hell, and the Grave on the behalf of eve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry true Believer; <hi>Rom.</hi> 8.37. <hi>Nay in all theſe Things, we are more then Conquerours through him that hath loved us.</hi> This gaſh<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ly Enemy, the grim King of Terrors, Death, muſt ſhortly be encounter'd by every one of us; as every Believer may, ſo them that are rightly aſſured can Tri<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>umph in Chriſt over them; they like <hi>Paul</hi> can give Death a bold challenge to do its worſt, 1 <hi>Cor.</hi> 15.55, 56, 57. <hi>O Death, where is thy ſting? O Grave, where is thy Victory? The ſting of Death is Sin, and the ſtrength of Sin is the Law; but thanks be to God, which giveth us the Victory through our Lord Jeſus Chriſt;</hi> Victory they have by Free Gift through Jeſus Chriſt, the Faith of Aſſurance often puts Believers upon deſiring and groan<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing to be diſſolved and why, though im<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mediately after Death comes Judgment; yet being cloathed upon, they ſhall not be found naked of Chriſts Righteouſneſs, 2 <hi>Cor.</hi> 5.3. <hi>If ſo be that being cloath'd, we ſhall not be found naked;</hi> hence it is that Believers, eſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cially ſuch that are ſeal'd with the Holy Spirit of Promiſe, they are ſaid to Love, and look for the appearing and come<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing of Chriſt to Judgment, 2 <hi>Tim.</hi> 4.8. <hi>Henceforth there is laid up for me a Crown of Righteouſneſs, which the Lord, the righteous Judge, ſhall give me at that Day, and not to me only, but unto all them alſo that Love his
<pb n="25" facs="tcp:32809:13"/>appearing.</hi> So in <hi>Heb.</hi> 9.28. <hi>Chriſt was once offered to bear the Sins of many, and unto them that look for him, ſhall be appear the ſecond Time, without Sin unto Salvation.</hi> They Love and look for Chriſts appearing, like as a loving Wife doth for the pleaſant return of her long abſent Husband: It could be no great Matter for <hi>Job</hi> to Die, for it was but to go to his living Redeemer; it could be no terrifying Thing to him to appear at the Bar of God, for he not only kept his In<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>tegrity unto the Laſt, but he knew that his powerful Advocate and Days-man was his living Redeemer. Thus I have finiſhed the Doctrinal Part of this Obſervation; <hi>viz.</hi> They are great and rare Inſtances of Grace, who can with Holy <hi>Job,</hi> upon Scripture Grounds ſay, <hi>They know that their Redeemer liveth.</hi> Now this Doctrine might be appli<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed many Ways, but to Contract:</p>
            <p n="1">1. Know that the greatneſs and rarity of this Grace is no effectual Bar to the thing it ſelf; though it be great Grace, and a ſpe<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>cial Favour, yet it is poſſible and attainable; the <hi>Papiſts</hi> and <hi>Arminians</hi> erre greatly by de<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nying the poſſibility of Aſſurance, in the true and proper Scripture Sence of it. Is not the Effect of Chriſts Righteouſneſs appre<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>hended by Faith, <hi>Peace, Quietneſs, and Aſ<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſurance for ever?</hi> Yea <hi>Iſa.</hi> 32.17. Doth not the Holy Ghoſt expreſly ſay. <hi>Theſe things have I written unto you that believe on the Name of the Son of God, that ye may know, that ye have
<pb n="26" facs="tcp:32809:14"/>Eternal Life,</hi> 1 John 5.13. Is it not the ſpecial Office of the Spirit to Witneſs and Seal up our Intereſt in Chriſt? 1 <hi>John</hi> 5.8. <hi>There are Three that bear Witneſs in Earth, the Spirit, and the Water, and the Blood, and theſe Three agree in one.</hi> Moreover, are not we required to <hi>give Diligence, to make our Calling and Election ſure?</hi> 2. Pet. 1.10. Let me add, have not ſome of Chriſts faithful Servants attain'd to it in this Life? if the Deceaſed had not experienced this great Grace, if he had not been one of theſe rare Inſtances, you had not been thus entertain'd, by this Subject at preſent. Now that you may attain to this rich Grace, and have an experimental diſcerning that you are in the bleſſed number of theſe rare Inſtances. Take this Advice.</p>
            <p n="1">1. Stedfaſtly believe, that a well ground<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ed Aſſurance is attainable, but withall take heed of the two common Extreams, which<g ref="char:punc">▪</g> abound much in this preſent Age; <hi>viz.</hi> do not with ſome deny the poſſibility of the thing, nor with others (who know not ex<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>perimentally the way of the Spirit in work<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing this) I ſay, do not with them preſume upon it without Scripture warrant, theſe both muſt be carefully ſhun'd; they are ve<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry hazardous, to the Peace, Comfort, and welfare of immortal Souls.</p>
            <p n="2">2. Hope, that in the uſe of appointed means you may be favour'd with it. Say not there is no hope, as God hath not excluded you,
<pb n="27" facs="tcp:32809:14"/>ſo do not you ſhut out your ſelves. The very command to give Diligence, imports a deſign and poſſibility of the Thing; 2. <hi>Pet.</hi> 1.10. <hi>Give Diligence to make your Cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ling and Election ſure.</hi> Methinks the Grace and Authority herein contain'd, ſhould move you to ſtrive and endeavour after it; yea to conclude though not for, yet in ſo doing it is poſſible for you, and you in particular; do not only propound Grace neceſſary to Salvation in the uſe of the means, but level and aim at this, even to know like <hi>Job, That your Redeemer liveth.</hi>
            </p>
            <p n="3">3. Would you attain to this Grace, <hi>viz.</hi> (a well grounded Aſſurance of your intereſt in the living, Redeemer) then with Dili<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>gence attend to the Miniſtry of the Word; even that which hath a Teſtimony in your Conſciences, that it is the Miniſtry of the Goſpel, and hath the Adminiſtration of the Spirit going along with it. Not only Faith, <hi>Rom.</hi> 10.17. But alſo this Aſſurance comes by Hearing, and what an incouraging Pro<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>miſe is that which you have in <hi>Hoſea</hi> 6.3. <hi>Then ſhall we know, if we follow on to know the Lord, his going forth is prepar'd as the Morn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing, and he ſhall come unto us as the Rain, as the latter and the former Rain unto the Earth.</hi> O what hold is here for Faith, mark, his go<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing forth is prepar'd, and prepar'd as the Morning; now how doth the Morning go forth? Why certainly, gradually, irreſiſta<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>bly and exceeding comfortably? Why thus
<pb n="28" facs="tcp:32809:15"/>will the Lord diſcover himſelf to the re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>deem'd; but remember then, <hi>you muſt follow on,</hi> not play faſt and looſe; take ſome ſteps and then turn out of the war, but you muſt with this Promiſe, like a Staff in your hand, <hi>follow on to know the Lord.</hi> In this his ordina<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ry Way he ſealeth up Believers unto the Day of Redemption: Is Chriſt a living and Life giving Redeemer, then why may not you have Life in and from him? Hath he by the Price of his Blood, and the Power of his Spirit redeemed precious Souls: Why may not the Vertue of the one, and the Power of the other incloſe and ſave you? Is he exalted in our Natures, then why may not you be pittied and reliev'd by him? Will he ſtand upon the Earth in the latter Day, and in a Triumphant Manner to Judge the World, then except the Judge be your Advocate, you'll periſh for ever.</p>
            <p n="4">4. As the Goſpel reveals Chriſt to poor Sinners, ſo put forth the Hand of Faith and receive him; you are under command to believe, and that without delay, 1 <hi>John</hi> 3. 23. No preſent Indiſpoſition removes the Obligation, put not thoſe blocks in your Way, which Chriſt in the Goſpel has re<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>mov'd. What though Sinners are naturally impotent, yet who knows, but if you heark<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>en, his Power ſhall be exerted; the Poor Man did not Object his Hand was wither'd, but when his Heart was toward Chriſts Grace and Power: He found it went out
<pb n="29" facs="tcp:32809:15"/>with the Command, and his wither'd hand was reſtor'd and made whole; ſee <hi>Mat.</hi> 
               <gap reason="illegible" resp="#UOM" extent="1 letter">
                  <desc>•</desc>
               </gap>2.13. The living Redeemer, is Lord of Life and Glory; when the Word went out of his Mouth, you know how <hi>Thomas</hi> reply'd my Lord and my God, <hi>John</hi> 20.28.</p>
            <p n="5">5. Take heed of grieving the Spirit, but underſtand, and examine your ſelves in the way of his ſealing and conſirming Souls. I ſhall not touch upon the immediate and me<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>diate Way of the Spirits Witneſs, you have not only heard, but experienced the thing it ſelf in both Parts. But ah alas, it is Ig<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>norance of this which makes ſome preſume, and it is unacquaintedneſs with this which makes thee ſafe in the Hands of Chriſt, to fear they ſhall be miſerable for ever. O that you were skilful in this matter, the Lord lead you into this Truth, <hi>viz.</hi> The right way of the Spirits ſealing and aſſuring Souls.</p>
            <p>Now you will expect, that I ſhould ſpeak ſomething of what hath occaſioned this Sub<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ject; you know it is ſomewhat more than ordinary, two related to us, both Interred in one Week, deſir'd this Text might be ſpoke from. The one was a Private Mem<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ber, the other a Publick Perſon; your choice and my Fellow-Helper in the Work of the Goſpel. It is not my way to ſpeak much of the Dead, I had rather that Perſons Lives and Good Works, than my Lips, ſhould be the Trumpets of their Praiſes; but in this I
<pb n="30" facs="tcp:32809:16"/>may not be altogether ſilent, Mr. <hi>Philip King</hi> for his Time and ſtanding was a burn<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and ſhining Light, you could rejoyce in it but for a ſeaſon; becauſe a violent Feaver extinguiſht his Lamp in the Twenty Fifth Year of his Age. And now, when God is cutting off his faithful Watchmen, ſhall not we that remain tell you what of the Night? It is evident, God hath a Controverſie with us, for his Embaſſadors are call'd home; not only the Aged and Honourable whoſe Labours commend them to all judicious and ingenious Chriſtians: But alſo, our budding Hopes are cut off in great meaſure by the ſurprizing Death of the riſing Generati<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>on; not only the Reverend Dr. <hi>Bates,</hi> and Worthy Mr. <hi>Mead,</hi> but ſome of our hope<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ful Young Ones, Mr. S — Mr. <hi>King</hi> are gone alſo. Formerly God gave us ma<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ny faithful Witneſſes in Time of reſtraint, but now we have Liberty, what have we elſe? Now our <hi>Elijah</hi>'s Mantels are dropt off, O that a double Portion of the Spirit might be upon the ſucceeding <hi>Eliſha</hi>'s. But you of this Congregation, behold what the Lord hath done, and humbly enquire into the meaning of this ſad Providence; doth not this Rod loudly call for the Unity of the Spi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>rit in the Bond of Peace and Love? conform to it for the Lords ſake. I need not inform you, that the Deceaſed was one of theſe rare Inſtances of Grace; was not his ſhort abode with us a live Comment upon this Text. Did
<pb n="31" facs="tcp:32809:16"/>not almoſt every Prayer, and every Sermon, declare that he was upon the Coeleſtial Wrings of a well grounded Aſſurance; and ſo com<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ſequently as they were for him: Indeed he was of an emi<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>nent Spirit for powerful Godlineſs. I know not what Suffering-Work he was ever cal<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>led out unto, but his Acquaintance with the Myſteries of the Goſpel, his Patience in Sickneſs, and his Triumph in Death was all more than Ordinary; by theſe things we have fair warning, God help us to take it, leſt worſt befal us; not hardening, but teach<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>ing and humbling Afflictions are New-Co<g ref="char:EOLhyphen"/>venant Mercies. So much for this Text, and Time, the Lord give you Underſtanding in all Things.</p>
            <trailer>FINIS.</trailer>
         </div>
      </body>
   </text>
</TEI>
